<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Epithalamium vpon the all-desired nvptials of Frederike the fift, Prince Palatine of Rhene, chiefe elector, Duke of Bauier, and arch-sewer to the Romane Empire And Elizabeth, the onely daughter of Iames, by the grace of God, King of Great Britain, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. VVritten by Augustine Taylor.</title>
            <author>Taylor, Augustine.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102628</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838400</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838400</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2776</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13412)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2776)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1118:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Epithalamium vpon the all-desired nvptials of Frederike the fift, Prince Palatine of Rhene, chiefe elector, Duke of Bauier, and arch-sewer to the Romane Empire And Elizabeth, the onely daughter of Iames, by the grace of God, King of Great Britain, France and Ireland, Defender of the Faith, &amp;c. VVritten by Augustine Taylor.</title>
                  <author>Taylor, Augustine.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[11] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Nicholas Okes] for Samuel Rand, and are to bee sold by Edward Marchant, at his shop in Pauls church-yard, ouer against the crosse,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴(-C4).</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 251) on title page.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: An epithalamium.</note>
                  <note>Some print faded and show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Elizabeth, --  Queen, consort of Frederick I, King of Bohemia, 1596-1662 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Epithalamium</hi> VPON THE ALL-DESIRED NVPTIALS of FREDERIKE the fift, Prince Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine of Rhene, chiefe Elector, Duke of Bauier, and Arch-Sewer to the Romane EMPIRE. <hi>AND ELIZABETH,</hi> The onely daughter of IAMES, by the grace of God, King of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, France and Ireland, Defender of the FAITH, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Written by AVGVSTINE TAYLOR.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Illi poena datur, qui ſemper amat, nec amatur.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Samuel Rand,</hi> and are to bee ſold by <hi>Edward Marchant,</hi> at his ſhop in Pauls Church-yard, ouer againſt the Croſſe. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: missing" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> GENTLEMAN, SIR Thomas Gerrard of Brinne, Knight Barronet, and one of his Maieſties Iuſtices for the Countie of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> AVGVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TINE TAYLOR wiſheth all proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity in Happineſse.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worthy Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>HEN all the excellent admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red wits of this ſo capable Age, in the ſpring of thicke furnitur'd inuentions, beſtow paines to giue my Patrons a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect blazon, I willing to thruſt my dutifull loue into the Preſſe, longing to ſee the ſhape of affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in Print; <hi>Credo vt eſt dementia,</hi> Seeing ſo many ſwelling Muſes, and of ſuch apprehenſion, that read theirs and mine next together, and you will ſay, my ill worke makes their good labours to appeare better then (indeed) they are. <hi>Vt ſementem feceris, ita &amp; metes:</hi> Apply not that Rule to mee, but right worthy Sir, of what I offer willingly, vouch to accept courteouſly, as a Monument of my loue, which
<pb facs="tcp:2776:3"/> time hath borne to the generous family of the <hi>Gerrards,</hi> and my affection to your worthy ſelfe. Knowing you to come from the beſt worth of that Aierie, and one of his Maieſties reſpected, grace my ill-tempered Muſe: and hauing ſo worthy a refuge, you ſhall hereafter ſee it ſtart out of Cinders <hi>(vnus dies non ſat eſtad parandam eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionem)</hi> and liue an age that ere-while waxt old with a Sommers day. Vouch to allow of this, till time preſent you with ſome greater token of my loue: I commit your deſeruing worthineſſe to wiſhed continuance.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in loue and dutie, AVGVSTINE TAYLOR</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Volenti nihil eſt graue.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="epithalamium">
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:3"/>
            <head>Facile eſt imperare volenti.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>O Would to God I had the Sun-hatch't wing,</l>
               <l>A quill ſo worth to tell of banquetting:</l>
               <l>Mine is ſo partcht in cinders of my wants,</l>
               <l>Deſert craues Vowels, Art giues Conſonants.</l>
               <l>One ſence is ſleeping, and that ſence is muffled,</l>
               <l>This ſence is ſtudying, that and all are ruffled:</l>
               <l>Amazed, wakened, called, incompoſed,</l>
               <l>Moued, affected, gathered, indiſcloſed.</l>
               <l>The perfect blazon true fame ſhall ſupport,</l>
               <l>Will tell how farre my Art is heere too ſhort:</l>
               <l>Were I but ſeated on the Muſes mountaine,</l>
               <l>To quaffe my quart of that ripe dropping fountaine,</l>
               <l>Where <hi>Tully</hi> once wonne that immortall praiſe,</l>
               <l>From that <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> fetcht his Romaine phraſe:</l>
               <l>Vnder that <hi>Helicon</hi> my Muſe ſhould ſing,</l>
               <l>Not altogether praiſe of <hi>Englands</hi> King,</l>
               <l>But in my notes Fames whiſpering breath ſhould bleed,</l>
               <l>Deſeruing praiſes to his worthy ſeed.</l>
               <l>You now muſt thinke I felt my wit but poore,</l>
               <l>I napt an howre, and ment to write no more.</l>
               <l>Now apparitions, now good, and then bad,</l>
               <l>I'le tell thee <hi>England</hi> of a dreame I had.</l>
               <l>Suppoſe I ſate vpon the Cliffes of <hi>Douer,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>(From flowery <hi>Kent</hi>) the Ocean to looke ouer.</l>
               <l>When in a morning old <hi>Aurora's</hi> hue</l>
               <l>Had clad the heauens in their ancient blew.</l>
               <l>Night went ſo faſt, and day appear'd ſo plaine,</l>
               <l>The eies diſeaſed of the Northerne waine:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Artipholax</hi> bluſter'd in his muffled bed,</l>
               <l>Pale <hi>Luna</hi> to the Weſterne confines fled;</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:4"/>
               <l>White teames of miſt ran ſtealing downe the riuers,</l>
               <l>Eclipſed manſions now were craz'd in ſhiuers,</l>
               <l>My greedy ſlumber ſhew'd my eies, me thought</l>
               <l>Strange nouelties that cheerefull day had brought.</l>
               <l>The firſt I gaz'd at, ſeem'd a rocke of ſtone,</l>
               <l>Which Sea-gods (ſometime) vſ'd to ſit vpon,</l>
               <l>Incompaſt round with ſeas on euery ſide,</l>
               <l>Fram'd like a ſeat, caſt by the ſurly tide;</l>
               <l>Whereon the faireſt Lady was repos'd,</l>
               <l>That euer Nature whilome had diſclos'd,</l>
               <l>Crown'd in all glory, made ſo fine and denty,</l>
               <l>I ſaw one beauty, and in that one plenty.</l>
               <l>If euer eye was ſummond to a feaſt,</l>
               <l>My eyes were feaſted, and my feaſt was beſt:</l>
               <l>I thought <hi>Marpeſſa</hi> in that princely Chaire</l>
               <l>Had there repos'd her ſelfe to take the aire,</l>
               <l>And ſadly ſuited in a ſolemne cheere,</l>
               <l>Did meane to ſtay her Lord and Louer there.</l>
               <l>And <hi>Idas</hi> ſlow, in needy ſpeed diſpatching,</l>
               <l>He yet was abſent, and ſhe yet was watching.</l>
               <l>O how I curſt him, (angry at delay)</l>
               <l>Hard-hearted man to be ſo long away.</l>
               <l>The day waxt elder, and the morne ſhew'd cleerer,</l>
               <l>The heauens pittifull, ſent the Sunne to cheere her.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Phoebus</hi> appear'd, cloth'd in his fair'ſt array,</l>
               <l>As if prepar'd to ſuite a glorious day.</l>
               <l>His radiant ſplendors ſcatter in the skyes,</l>
               <l>Her faire perfections ſparkle in mine eyes.</l>
               <l>I was opinionate the world was done,</l>
               <l>I thought the Gods had ſent another Sunne.</l>
               <l>Then it was ſo, by vcnturing, I came</l>
               <l>Some paces neerer to this princely Dame.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:4"/>
               <l>When I perceiu'd ſhe was a mortall creature,</l>
               <l>Compoſed in the perfect'ſt mould of Nature,</l>
               <l>And in her hand ſhe held a little frame,</l>
               <l>With this deuice erected in her name.</l>
            </lg>
            <floatingText type="device">
               <body>
                  <head>DELPHEBA.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A branch in March, that dy'd to liue in Aprill.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <p>Motto. <hi>Mors emit vitam.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <lg>
               <l>Life weeps for death, death crownes a new life bleſt;</l>
               <l>Thus, friends weep moſt, to know their friends at reſt.</l>
               <l>In this faire creature ſeated thus alone,</l>
               <l>A thouſand beauties were combin'd in one:</l>
               <l>Her golden Treſſes hang'd vncurl'd and ruffl'd,</l>
               <l>In a rich Night-gowne ſhe was ſadly muffl'd.</l>
               <l>O had I ſeene her ſuited in thoſe rayes,</l>
               <l>Which Courtly cuſtome obſerues now-a-dayes,</l>
               <l>I eould haue teld yee neerer her great merit,</l>
               <l>But ignorance muſt now a part inherit.</l>
               <l>Your thoughts muſt cenſure, ſhe was more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faire,</l>
               <l>(And being more, I cannot more declare)</l>
               <l>And fit to adde a glory to the sky,</l>
               <l>A mate (indeed) for maieſty to buy,</l>
               <l>Crown'd with all graces, and to name in generall,</l>
               <l>One beauty matchleſſe, and in that one ſeuerall.</l>
               <l>O had you ſeene her, how all beauties mou'd her,</l>
               <l>You wold haue prais'd her, if you had not lou'd her.</l>
               <l>Thus long I view'd her, rauiſht more &amp; more,</l>
               <l>I turn'd my eyes to glance vpon the ſhore,</l>
               <l>Where I eſpy'd a ſtranger ſadly ſtanding,</l>
               <l>Waiting for ſhipping, as men do for landing.</l>
               <l>Vpon <hi>Delphebaes</hi> ſeat his eyes were gazing,</l>
               <l>I ſaw a ſcutchion by the ſunnes bright blazing;</l>
               <l>Telling his name, and ouer that was planted</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:5"/>
               <l>A faire deuiſe which no perfection wanted.</l>
            </lg>
            <floatingText type="device">
               <body>
                  <head>TORBINIVS.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A male Confeſſor to a female Prieſt.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <p>Motto <hi>Palam, voluntate.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <lg>
               <l>Great men are often actors of oppreſſion,</l>
               <l>And ſhe's the cauſe that I muſt make confeſſion.</l>
               <l>His eies gaz'd at <hi>Delpheba</hi> as before,</l>
               <l>(So ſhip-wrackt ſea-men vſe to do at ſhore)</l>
               <l>Afflicted, troubled, feared, and tormented,</l>
               <l>Diſtemper'd, blubber'd, ſad, and diſcontented,</l>
               <l>Complaining, ſorrowing, wiſhing, nothing gaining,</l>
               <l>Sighing, bewailing, crauing, not obtaining,</l>
               <l>Seeking for paſſage to <hi>Delphebas</hi> reſting,</l>
               <l>Vowing, affecting, calling, and proteſting,</l>
               <l>Vnto the Powers Diuine he plants prefers,</l>
               <l>He had but one life and that was hers.</l>
               <l>To raile on Nature then he doth beginne,</l>
               <l>That ſhe (vnkind) ordain'd him not to ſwimme:</l>
               <l>To breake his paſſions <hi>Phoebus</hi> look't more cheerely,</l>
               <l>And ſmil'd as if hee lou'd a louer deerely,</l>
               <l>And halfe reſolu'd to let <hi>Torbinius</hi> paſſe,</l>
               <l>From him to her, he ſhowes a bridge of glaſſe:</l>
               <l>Compoſd in all parts pleaſant to behold,</l>
               <l>Fram'd by Diuine Art, wonders manifold,</l>
               <l>Appear'd to gaze on, yet it ſeem'd ſo brittle,</l>
               <l>The paſſage dangerous and the ſafety little;</l>
               <l>But loue ſo forward in his owne attempts,</l>
               <l>And mixes ſowre harmes with fraile ſweet contents,</l>
               <l>Determines now, as men for women would do,</l>
               <l>To win his loue, or try what venturing could do;</l>
               <l>Enters the bridge with this raſh reſolution,</l>
               <l>To die for loue, confirmes the old concluſion,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:5"/>
               <l>And his boil'd humour in this ſort doth cheriſh,</l>
               <l>To paſſe the bridge, or in the midſt to periſh:</l>
               <l>And being diſtant from the ſandie ſide,</l>
               <l>Some meaſur'd paces, <hi>Neptune</hi> ſends the tide,</l>
               <l>And ſummons fenny ſubiects to new broyles,</l>
               <l>Collecting ſurges to maintaine new ſpoyles.</l>
               <l>The houering windes tumbl'd from <hi>Eolus</hi> wombe,</l>
               <l>And in the Ocean gan to digge their Tombe.</l>
               <l>The <hi>Titan</hi> Eſterne gates, perculliz'd, pale,</l>
               <l>Er'ſt calmes, now ſtormes, for guſts a bitter gale.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nereus</hi> warn'd the Sea-gods to theſe warres,</l>
               <l>And rul'd as Generall in theſe vpſtart iarres.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Torbinius</hi> being on the bridge of glaſſe,</l>
               <l>Look't downe and ſaw th'impatient billowes paſſe,</l>
               <l>And with his dul eares, hard the deafe winds mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble,</l>
               <l>And with his dim eyes ſaw the ſurges tumble.</l>
               <l>One waue did caper, and that billow wonder'd,</l>
               <l>This ſurge was angry, and that tempeſt thunder'd,</l>
               <l>Aſpiring, threatning death, or future ill,</l>
               <l>Shaping, preſenting accidents to kill.</l>
               <l>A hurrying miſt comes ſudden ſtealing in,</l>
               <l>Nor he, nor ſhe, ſaw neither her nor him:</l>
               <l>In this ſtrange temper paſſionately diſtracted,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Torbinius</hi> now a ſowre part ſadly acted;</l>
               <l>And all his griefes ſprung, as it ſeem'd to me,</l>
               <l>From the ſicke confines of perplexitie.</l>
               <l>A thicke-lin'd miſt continu'd 'tweene them two,</l>
               <l>(Loue wrapt in wrinkles knowes no worke to do.)</l>
               <l>Thus Fortune makes, &amp; thus mad Forune marres,</l>
               <l>Loue is ſtill Souldier at ſuch ciuill warres.</l>
               <l>Sighing, lamenting, theſe bad broyles to be in,</l>
               <l>That he ſhould dye, and not his Lady ſee him,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:6"/>
               <l>When onely for her ſake hee ventured thus,</l>
               <l>(Loue ſees no dangers that ſeeme timorus.)</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Torbinius.</hi>
                  </note>Then to himſelfe (I thought) hee did reply,</l>
               <l>And ſaid; How luckleſſe and accurſt am I,</l>
               <l>Couer'd with fortunes foule diſſembling fame,</l>
               <l>To dye for her that knowes not who I am?</l>
               <l>Oh might I dye my Ladies face before,</l>
               <l>I would ſay Fortune were a noble Whore,</l>
               <l>In her faire ſight to end <hi>Torbinius</hi> date,</l>
               <l>O then my death were not vnfortunate,</l>
               <l>Then ſhe might iuſtly ſay; here ended he,</l>
               <l>That liu'd, and lou'd, and dy'd to honor me:</l>
               <l>But Gods, &amp; Seas, &amp; Winds, contemne my plaints,</l>
               <l>And their harſh Language trippes on Conſonants:</l>
               <l>Then thus reſolu'd, ſucceed what ill can proue,</l>
               <l>And if I dye, I dye for her I loue.</l>
               <l>I left him thus, and turn'd my greedy eyes</l>
               <l>Vpon the rocke where faire <hi>Delpheba</hi> lyes,</l>
               <l>Who now in blacke appear'd to me all couer'd,</l>
               <l>About the which ſad Melancholy houer'd.</l>
               <l>Then to <hi>Delpheba</hi> there (me thought) reſorted,</l>
               <l>Nymphes and Sea-gods, by their loue tranſported,</l>
               <l>To comfort her that ſeem'd ſo much lamenting,</l>
               <l>And know the ſad cauſe of her diſcontenting.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Delpheba.</hi>
                  </note>To whom ſhe anſwer'd, I haue loſt a friend,</l>
               <l>Which winged <hi>Fame</hi> can nere too much commend.</l>
               <l>O would to God I could <hi>Olimpus</hi> raiſe,</l>
               <l>And there ſet Trophies to his endleſſe praiſe:</l>
               <l>And for his death, I choſe this place to mone,</l>
               <l>"The teares are trueſt that are ſhed alone."</l>
               <l>A dying life weepes for a liuing death,</l>
               <l>A tale vnſeemely for a true friends breath.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:6"/>
               <l>And as it is, it may be ſomething better,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fortune's</hi> a ſtrumpet, and ſhe is my debter,</l>
               <l>Promiſing beſt, when ſhe perform'd the worſt:</l>
               <l>Things that ſound harſhli'ſt, I haue had thoſe firſt.</l>
               <l>The Gods and Nymphs began to tune their throtes,</l>
               <l>To keepe a conſort with her cheereleſſe notes.</l>
               <l>In this <hi>Diapaſon</hi> deepe, ſad harmonie,</l>
               <l>Dull ſences ſtriue for ſorrowes victory,</l>
               <l>Chimes iterating on this blacke-mouth'd dinne;</l>
               <l>I then perceiu'd <hi>Torbinius</hi> comming in,</l>
               <l>Seeing <hi>Delpheba</hi> in ſuch paſſions ſuited,</l>
               <l>In mourning weeds ſuch ill cheere proſecuted,</l>
               <l>Attires himſelfe in ſorrowes for her ſake,</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Torbinius.</hi>
                  </note>The Counter-tennor of her part to take.</l>
               <l>Vnto the fair'ſt my ſeruice I commend,</l>
               <l>Tis onely thou my loue did apprehend,</l>
               <l>All dangers paſt compared to this prize,</l>
               <l>Seemes like a darke way to a Paradize.</l>
               <l>And on all dangers what's he would not venter,</l>
               <l>Thoſe all being paſt, might to thy preſence enter?</l>
               <l>And am I happy to be comne thus neere thee?</l>
               <l>And art thou kind? or can my comming cheere thee?</l>
               <l>I'le weare what thou wears, what thou loues Ile keep</l>
               <l>I'le laugh whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſmiles, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou ſighes Ile weep.</l>
               <l>What moſt ſhall grieue thee, it ſhal moſt torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me,</l>
               <l>What beſt ſhal pleaſe thee, that ſhal beſt conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t me.</l>
               <l>If Natures pride be but ſo kinde as faire,</l>
               <l>All ſtormes are paſt, I do not care for Care.</l>
               <l>I loue thee now when ſad laments increaſe,</l>
               <l>To haue thy loue when paſſions turne to peace.</l>
               <l>Expecting Sommer when cold March is paſt,</l>
               <l>I'le wait ten months to haue a May at laſt.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:7"/>
               <l>Il'e reape no Harueſt but where thou haſt ſowne,</l>
               <l>My loue in thy loue ſhall exceed thy owne.</l>
               <l>And but in thee, no hope, no hap, no health,</l>
               <l>And but in thee no will, no wiſh, no wealth.</l>
               <l>For what thou mournes, I waile, thy part I take;</l>
               <l>Now bleſſed be all women for thy ſake.</l>
               <l>In thee I loue, in thee I onely liue,</l>
               <l>'Tis I that begges, and it is thou can giue.</l>
               <l>Nor do I craue thee more then may beſeeme thee,</l>
               <l>Thou art my beſt hap, and I moſt eſteeme thee.</l>
               <l>Make me a ſeruant at thy ſacred ſhrine;</l>
               <l>This life is that life, let that life be mine.</l>
               <l>What good, what ill, what life, what all to thee,</l>
               <l>That good, that ill, that life, that all to me.</l>
               <l>Comforts attend thee, all good hap befriend thee,</l>
               <l>Duties commend thee, wiſhed power defend thee.</l>
               <l>Make me thy ſeruant, ſmile on my requeſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Delphebaes</hi> Scholler I am now profeſt.</l>
               <l>At <hi>Lunaes</hi> full the skyes ſeeme in their ſtate,</l>
               <l>At Princes birthes the earth lookes fortunate.</l>
               <l>The one decayes when in her chiefeſt prime,</l>
               <l>The other dyes when in his hopeful'ſt time.</l>
               <l>My teares are falling for a friend that lou'd me,</l>
               <l>He's dead, he's gone, &amp; thus his death hath mou'd me</l>
               <l>His death is liuing, and my life is dying,</l>
               <l>My life is creeping, and his death is flying.</l>
               <l>My loſſe, his gaine: his wealth my wo compriz'd,</l>
               <l>Are two contraries ſtrangely exerciz'd.</l>
               <l>My plaints and teares, and ſorrowes, ſtill augmented,</l>
               <l>Complaining, blubber'd, laſting more tormented.</l>
               <l>Much pitty'd cheereneſſe, much lamented neerneſſe,</l>
               <l>Vnharbor'd, feareleſſe, vnfrequented neereneſſe,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:7"/>
               <l>Deſolate, diſtreſſed, fruſtrate, vn-reſpected,</l>
               <l>Incommitate, oppreſſed, complicate, neglected:</l>
               <l>And of all theſe ills there is but one mother,</l>
               <l>Pale Death, leaues our life this gift, and no other.</l>
               <l>The earth and Mortals muſt ſubmit their Powers,</l>
               <l>To ſerue a VVill aboue this will of ours.</l>
               <l>Of what earth can do I may iuſtly vaunt,</l>
               <l>VVhat heauens will haue I muſt needly grant.</l>
               <l>O death, ô death, thy ſpoiles I cannot mend,</l>
               <l>Yet I'le performe the duty of a friend:</l>
               <l>Some friends liue yet, 'tis you appeares to me</l>
               <l>VVill be aſſociate in my miſery.</l>
               <l>You, you, <hi>Torbinius,</hi> for your great deſert,</l>
               <l>Shall haue the beſt place in my conquer'd heart:</l>
               <l>My loue, ſhall your loue pay with wiſht reward,</l>
               <l>And with <hi>Delpheba</hi> be in beſt regard:</l>
               <l>Expecting ſorrowes will be ſooner paſt,</l>
               <l>And ioy (though long) yet will be here at laſt:</l>
               <l>The skies look cheerly, that e're-while lok't ſtrangly,</l>
               <l>The ſeas are ſmiling that but now were angry,</l>
               <l>I thinke the Gods (together) haue decreed</l>
               <l>To change our muffled melancholy weed,</l>
               <l>And for our late lamented Funerals,</l>
               <l>Now to erect contented Nuptials;</l>
               <l>In pledge of loue I greete thee with a kiſſe,</l>
               <l>I owe thee more, ſuppoſe, by giuing this.</l>
               <l>Now let me craue you to decide this thought</l>
               <l>And be not partiall; which of theſe two ought</l>
               <l>To be lamented more? her teares are ſowne,</l>
               <l>For her friends harueſt that pale death hath mowne:</l>
               <l>His teares are ſpent for her calamities,</l>
               <l>That ſeemes a mother of ſad miſeries.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:8"/>
               <l>Shee weepes for him that neuer can do better,</l>
               <l>Hee weepes for her that yet is natures debter:</l>
               <l>Then rightly ſcan'd if iudgement rightly do,</l>
               <l>'Twill ſay her teares, no wiſe worke takes them too:</l>
               <l>Whether ſhe weepe for freind ſake, or her owne,</l>
               <l>'Tis yet a queſtion, and it is not knowne,</l>
               <l>If for her owne ſake (I muſt needs be plaine)</l>
               <l>Shee thought by his life to reape future gaine;</l>
               <l>This wailing no man rightly can commend,</l>
               <l>For thus ſhe proues a very vnkind freind.</l>
               <l>If ſhe lament for his ſake, wiſe men ſaith,</l>
               <l>Shee ſhowes th'imbecillity of her faith.</l>
               <l>And by that weakeneſſe it appeares to me</l>
               <l>Shee thinkes her ſelfe in better caſe then he:</l>
               <l>She ought not t'weepe that he hath run ſo faſt,</l>
               <l>But at her ſlow pace that muſt go at laſt.</l>
               <l>But now (me-thinkes) <hi>Delphebas</hi> wondrous wiſe,</l>
               <l>To make a Summer of her Winters eies:</l>
               <l>All friendly duties are diſcharged duly,</l>
               <l>Old Natures loue is paid by wiſedome truly.</l>
               <l>The Sun, and Aire, &amp; houering Winds do mutter,</l>
               <l>Conceiuing more ioy, then dumbe ſence can vtter:</l>
               <l>The Sea-gods whiſper iump in all opinions,</l>
               <l>To order peace through their vntil'd Dominions,</l>
               <l>And tooke their leaue, all Tempeſts now are gone,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Torbinius</hi> and <hi>Delpheba</hi> now alone,</l>
               <l>They ioyned hands and then (me thought) did paſſe</l>
               <l>Backe to the ſhore where great attending was,</l>
               <l>And being landed dangers all bereft them,</l>
               <l>My dreame was ended and in ioy I left them.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:8"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Ex aſpectis naſcitur amor.</head>
               <l>When Lordly <hi>Phaebus</hi> left his Eſterne Ile,</l>
               <l>And with his ſplendor that <hi>Titanian</hi> ſmile,</l>
               <l>Came like a Prince from th'orientall gate,</l>
               <l>So richly ſuted in his robes of State.</l>
               <l>The cheareleſſe earth ſhooke off her dewy treſſes,</l>
               <l>And from darke curtaines now her ſhades digreſſes.</l>
               <l>I lookt about me, <hi>Douer</hi> was not neere mee,</l>
               <l>That now contents me, which but then did feare me.</l>
               <l>I then perceiu'd 'twas on the bancke of Thames,</l>
               <l>That I retain'd th'inuention of my dreames:</l>
               <l>And as the pleaſant Riuer faſt did glide,</l>
               <l>With pratling murmur by the <hi>Kentiſh</hi> ſide,</l>
               <l>I laid me downe neere to a Willow roote,</l>
               <l>Whoſe branches farre had ouer-growne the foote;</l>
               <l>The ſearching Sunne not in a day obtain'd,</l>
               <l>To ſee the ſtocke whereby ſhe was maintain'd.</l>
               <l>'Twas publicke knowne a fairer tree then this,</l>
               <l>Ne're neighbour'd neere the bankes of <hi>Thameſis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>I there repos'd vpon this dewy brimme.</l>
               <l>And, as I thought, the Tide came ſtealing in.</l>
               <l>Thames that e're while gaz'd vpon <hi>Phoebus</hi> prime,</l>
               <l>Turn'd now againe to watch for his decline:</l>
               <l>Night went, day came, all ioyes on tiptoes ſhiuer,</l>
               <l>A ſnow white Swanne came playing vp the Riuer:</l>
               <l>Ruffling his plumes and in ſuch ioy did ſwimme,</l>
               <l>You would haue ſworne the Tide much fauor'd him.</l>
               <l>His ſo faire breaſt dinted the furrowing <hi>Iſis,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>VVho ſaith he ſaw a worthier bird then this is?</l>
               <l>Both <hi>Kent</hi> and <hi>Eſſex</hi> gather'd neere to ſee,</l>
               <l>VVhere the firſt landing of this Swanne might bee:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:9"/>
               <l>Faire <hi>Middle-ſex</hi> pul'd downe her maske and Fan,</l>
               <l>To ſee the Tide bring in this ſtranger Swan.</l>
               <l>O how it ioy'd me to heare muſicke greet him</l>
               <l>In ſeuerall tunes, and other Swannes did meete him;</l>
               <l>Their Princely ſalutations ſure were ſuch,</l>
               <l>As <hi>London</hi> neuer ſaw of mirth ſo much.</l>
               <l>Now, in the end, where this faire Swan took landing,</l>
               <l>Let none decide but thoſe of vnderſtanding.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Quiſque poteſt rebus ſuccurrere, nemo diebus.</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke. Omnia fert tempus.</hi>
                  </note>VVhen thou (great Prince) from <hi>Rhenus</hi> natiue clime</l>
               <l>(Richer then <hi>Tagus,</hi> faire as <hi>Florentine,</hi>)</l>
               <l>Pul'd vp thy Enſignes, clad thy ratling Sailes,</l>
               <l>The wind, thy vyage, and the Tide preuailes,</l>
               <l>To bring thee to our Eaſterne tumbling Thames,</l>
               <l>The Ocean's meſſage to great <hi>Britaines</hi> IAMES:</l>
               <l>And may that howre in happy times to come</l>
               <l>Be cal'd thy landing in <hi>Elizium:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Happy thy birth, more fortunate thy life,</l>
               <l>Proſperous thy voyage, vertuous thy wife:</l>
               <l>Vertue, Virginity, Honour, Natures pride,</l>
               <l>Thou art her Husband, and Shee is thy Bride,</l>
               <l>And conſecrated ſhall that day be thought:</l>
               <l>The howre and <hi>Iſis</hi> that thee hither brought,</l>
               <l>Shall be erected in great Fames Regiſter,</l>
               <l>And thy reward is prou'd a Princes Siſter.</l>
               <l>Fame cannot chuſe but impe her pinion'd wing,</l>
               <l>And in loud Muſicke for thy welcome ſing:</l>
               <l>Feaſt thee, attend thee, and in more eſteeme</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Cleopatra</hi> the <hi>Egiptian</hi> Queene</l>
               <l>Feaſted <hi>Marke Anthony,</hi> nor can thou ſay,</l>
               <l>Thou came in Autumne, it was rather May;</l>
               <l>Onely croſſes of lamented Funerals,</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:9"/>
               <l>Chanc't in the Frontiers of thy Nuptials.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xor bona, optima poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio.</hi>
                  </note>O worthy FREDERIKE, it was Lordly done,</l>
               <l>That thou thy ſelfe in perſon hither come.</l>
               <l>It ſhewes thy minde is Noble, and indeed,</l>
               <l>Sprung from the airie where true Eagles breed.</l>
               <l>Eagles in Cages, are but Kings in Towers,</l>
               <l>And but enioy the name of Princely powers.</l>
               <l>Kings are earths Gods, and Gods liu'd not at home,</l>
               <l>But had a mind in forraine Climes to rome.</l>
               <l>'Tis regiſter'd not many Ages ſince,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Solon</hi> of <hi>Athens</hi> was to chooſe a Prince:</l>
               <l>Being demanded how he meant to know,</l>
               <l>A man well worthy of a Crowne (or no)</l>
               <l>Anſwer'd: If this choyce be to me aſſig'nd,</l>
               <l>Il'e chooſe a Prince, and onely by the minde:</l>
               <l>If inward Noble, I heard wiſe men tell,</l>
               <l>Hee's worth a Crowne, and 'twill ſeeme paſſing wel.</l>
               <l>By this I noted, how thou truly merits</l>
               <l>The perfect beautie that thou now inherits,</l>
               <l>And ſure ſhe thinkes thee a right worthy Prince,</l>
               <l>That would thy trauels (for her ſake) conuince.</l>
               <l>If all that trauel'd might enioy like ſtore,</l>
               <l>The lame would run, that ſcarce could go before.</l>
               <l>Who would not trauell, and to them owe duties,</l>
               <l>VVhen each eye finds perfections in their beauties?</l>
               <l>Liue long, great Prince, and be thy choſen prize</l>
               <l>A faire terreſtriall happy Paradize.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>To Germany.</hi>
                  </note>In time hereafter, yet remember <hi>Thame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How once ſhe welcom'd a yong Prince of <hi>Rhene.</hi>
               </l>
               <trailer>Amicos nouos parans, ne obliuiſcaris veterum.</trailer>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:10"/>
            <lg>
               <head>Virtus in ſe habet omnia bona.</head>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To <hi>Elizab.</hi>
                  </note>Faire Princeſſe, vertuous; what to good belongs</l>
               <l>Thou art the mother to, Applauſe ſo throngs,</l>
               <l>T'attend on thee, and 'mongſt the reſt my part,</l>
               <l>It is thy merites makes my loue and Art,</l>
               <l>Vprear'd on tiptoes, and yet would aſpire</l>
               <l>To giue thee what is due, and my deſire,</l>
               <l>Tels but thy name, and it is all I can,</l>
               <l>Thoſe do no more, that profeſſe what I am:</l>
               <l>Nor can, nor neede, for all remembreth</l>
               <l>That thou art onely that <hi>Elizabeth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Which forraine Ecchoes in loud notes doth ring,</l>
               <l>To be the daughter of great <hi>Britaines</hi> King.</l>
               <l>Nor is it I that labours in thy praiſe,</l>
               <l>I know thy name's thy Trumpet, and can raiſe</l>
               <l>It ſelfe to'th' height of honour; why I write</l>
               <l>To tell my duty, and this Epithite,</l>
               <l>Is ſtuft full of Affection: what if poore?</l>
               <l>The gifts are great when giuers haue no more:</l>
               <l>And ſhould indeed be thought our <hi>Alexander,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Macedo's</hi> ſonne: the Eaſterne great Commander,</l>
               <l>Was nam'd in Cottages by th'low'ſt degree;</l>
               <l>Then of a Miller: ô good God ſaid hee,</l>
               <l>There's not a Miller now but knowes my name,</l>
               <l>Meaning indeed Report addes life to Fame;</l>
               <l>Fame's like the Sunne, and not diſdaines to view</l>
               <l>Both Courts and Cottages, neither doth rue</l>
               <l>Of their great courteſies: marke well each ſeate,</l>
               <l>And great men proud, makes them vnſeemely great.</l>
               <l>A woman ſilent, great by birth before,</l>
               <l>So richly dreſt, Fame ſhapeth more and more.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:10"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Eliza, England</hi> truly boaſts of thee</l>
               <l>To be the Treaſurer of each Treaſurie,</l>
               <l>That euer grac't a woman: muſt we leaue thee?</l>
               <l>Il'e now truſt Fortune; for't did not deceiue me.</l>
               <l>I euer thought ſo faire a flower as this,</l>
               <l>Should grace ſome other place then <hi>Thameſis.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And yet faire Princeſſe, vertuous I meane,</l>
               <l>Remember <hi>Thames</hi> when thou art ſet on <hi>Rhene.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>How gladly thunder'd ſhe lowd Epithets,</l>
               <l>Profeſſed peales, all to her Nuptiall Rites?</l>
               <l>Did ſhe not ſummon gazers to thy Reuels,</l>
               <l>And what was knotty, with her tide ſhe leuels?</l>
               <l>Diſ-gorged Canons fire in ſeuerall ſhapes,</l>
               <l>Enemies ſuffer when true Chriſtians ſcapes.</l>
               <l>Meteors i'th aire, ſhe did her owne ſelfe choake,</l>
               <l>All <hi>London</hi> thought <hi>Thames</hi> wold diſſolue to ſmoke,</l>
               <l>And all the Reuels this faire Floud did make,</l>
               <l>VVorthy <hi>Eliza,</hi> was but for thy ſake.</l>
               <l>VVhen thou waſt married, ſhe by chance heard tell,</l>
               <l>And did but this becauſe ſhe loues thee well.</l>
               <l>At thy depart, ſhee'l follow thee and weepe,</l>
               <l>And then ſhee'l turne thy worthy ſtocke to ſeeke,</l>
               <l>And finding them, ſhee'l leaue her ſobbing moane,</l>
               <l>Onely ſhee'l each day ſee where thou haſt gone.</l>
               <l>VVell may ſhe boaſt ſhe was of able power,</l>
               <l>To grace faire <hi>Rhenus</hi> with an <hi>Engliſh</hi> flower.</l>
               <l>And when theſe two meet in great Oceans,</l>
               <l>Thei'l know each other by their natiue Swans.</l>
               <l>So by this marriage, Eccho vnderſtands,</l>
               <l>'Twill make acquainted both the Seas and Lands.</l>
               <l>A happy time, a good world may it be,</l>
               <l>After yong <hi>Frederike</hi> came to match with thee.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:11"/>
               <l>O noted howre, bleſt be the God aboue,</l>
               <l>Thou but leaues <hi>England</hi> to enioy thy loue;</l>
               <l>And for thy abſence <hi>Britaine</hi> in a mends</l>
               <l>Hath gained great ſtore of true Chriſtian friends.</l>
               <l>Liue, liue, faire Princeſſe, may thy ſeede, thy fame,</l>
               <l>In cinders, aſhes keepe aliue thy name.</l>
               <trailer>Foelicitas eſt voluptas, quam paenitudo nulla ſequitur.</trailer>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Creator per creaturas cognoſcendus.</head>
               <l>
                  <hi>Heu,</hi> ſome will ſay when they haue loſt a friend</l>
               <l>And make his funerall, e're they ſee his end;</l>
               <l>A number now are buried in conceit</l>
               <l>When they'r (indeed) not ſicke, yet teares will wait.</l>
               <l>There is a death in abſence ſome ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>Who thinkes there is? for I am none of thoſe:</l>
               <l>Is <hi>England</hi> loth to looſe ſo faire a creature</l>
               <l>As art thy ſelfe <hi>Eliza?</hi> ô, Dame Nature</l>
               <l>Caſt thee not in her mould of beſt perfection,</l>
               <l>Euer to liue a Virgin, heauens direction</l>
               <l>Smil'd at thy birth and meant to make a mother,</l>
               <l>That when thou dies thou may leaue ſuch another.</l>
               <l>Virginity dies a Traitor, her poſſeſſions</l>
               <l>Like traitors Earldomes make ſuch large digreſſions</l>
               <l>They leaue no Heires at all, by this I ſee</l>
               <l>A Virgine cannot leaue poſterity.</l>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">To <hi>Elizab.</hi>
                  </note>As thou art honour'd for a Virgins life,</l>
               <l>Thou ſtill ſhalt liue, becauſe a happy wife.</l>
               <l>I heard it ſaid, the firſt time <hi>Neſtor</hi> ſmil'd,</l>
               <l>Was when he ſaw a woman great with child;</l>
               <l>And being asked why he ſmil'd (and bleſt her,)</l>
               <l>Said he, the next age will remember <hi>Neſtor.</hi>
               </l>
               <pb facs="tcp:2776:11"/>
               <l>And thou faire Princeſſe in the age to come,</l>
               <l>Shall liue by Fame when Natures life hath done:</l>
               <l>And death hath truely paid her Fame to time</l>
               <l>Shall build their blazons to the ſeed of thine.</l>
               <trailer>Fama velox eſt, creſcit<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> eundo.</trailer>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <l>LOue, like, leaue, looke at other ripe inuentions:</l>
            <l>And ſee how farre mine differs from the reſt:</l>
            <l>My dull conceite conceiues ſome apprehenſions,</l>
            <l>Theſe are indifferent, thoſe are of the beſt.</l>
            <l>Their's good, mine worſer, good may worſer ſmother,</l>
            <l>The beſt appeares beſt, when 'tis by the worſt:</l>
            <l>How can that be? yes; ſet by either other,</l>
            <l>And that which lookes beſt men will chooſe that firſt.</l>
            <l>Mine's poorely ſuted, yet my Patrons name's</l>
            <l>So ſeated in the fore-head of my Verſe,</l>
            <l>'Twill moue the Reader to beſtow ſome paines,</l>
            <l>And iterate that which I do rehearſe:</l>
            <l>And when thou finds my Poems barely dreſt,</l>
            <l>Smile to thy ſelfe (and ſay) he did his beſt.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>Auguſtine Taylor.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>Vbi timor, ibi pudor.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:12"/>
            <head>Laus in prima ſonat, virtus in fine coronat.</head>
            <l>
               <hi>FAme's yet an Infant, Eccho's of report,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Now impes her pinions, and in ſcattering ſort</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Applauds what good's in acting, generall praiſe</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Crownes the beginning, and the end to raiſe,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Vertue's about to giue a Lawrell wreath</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>To worthy</hi> Frederike <hi>and</hi> Elizabeth:</l>
            <l>
               <hi>VVhen Time the merits of your time hath gather'd,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>You ſhall appeare yong, when your time is wither'd.</hi>
            </l>
            <trailer>Praemia victorum pendent a fine laborum.</trailer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2776:12"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
